Manton Marble Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Manton Marble Papers 1838-1916 (bulk 1864-1898)
MSS31286
Marble, Manton, 1834-1917
14,000 items
97 containers
20.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Editor and publisher. Correspondence, drafts of articles and letters, financial papers, newspaper clippings, photographs, and other material relating to Marble’s career as editor and owner of the New York World, and as a senior member of the national Democratic Party.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Arnold, Samuel Greene, 1821-1880--Correspondence.; Barlow, Samuel L. M. (Samuel Latham Mitchill), 1826-1889--Correspondence.; Bayard, Thomas F. (Thomas Francis), 1828-1898--Correspondence.; Belmont, August, Sr., 1813-1890--Correspondence.; Bogart, W. H. (William Henry), 1810-1888--Correspondence.; Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908.; Comstock, Calvert, 1812-1876--Correspondence.; Cox, Samuel Sullivan, 1824-1889--Correspondence.; Croly, David G. (David Goodman), 1829-1889--Correspondence.; Curtis, George Ticknor, 1812-1894--Correspondence.; Dana, Charles A. (Charles Anderson), 1819-1897--Correspondence.; Doolittle, James R. (James Rood), 1815-1897--Correspondence.; Fiske, John, 1842-1901--Correspondence.; Hurlbert, William Henry, 1827-1895--Correspondence.; Johnson, Reverdy, 1796-1876--Correspondence.; Kerr, Michael C. (Michael Crawford), 1827-1876--Correspondence.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865.; Marble, Manton, 1834-1917.; Medill, Joseph, 1823-1899--Correspondence.; Porter, Fitz-John, 1822-1901--Correspondence.; Rathbone, John Finley, 1819- --Correspondence.; Seymour, Horatio, 1810-1886--Correspondence.; Spencer, Herbert, 1820-1903--Correspondence.; Stoddard, Richard Henry, 1825-1903--Correspondence.; Tilden, Samuel J. (Samuel Jones), 1814-1886--Correspondence.; Vallandigham, Clement L. (Clement Laird), 1820-1871--Correspondence.; Watterson, Henry, 1840-1921--Correspondence.; White, Horace, 1834-1916--Correspondence.
Organizations
Democratic Party (N.Y.); Democratic Party (U.S.)
Subjects
American newspapers--New York (State)--New York.; Bimetallism.; Elections--United States--1864.; Elections--United States--1876.; Silver question.
Places
Europe--Foreign relations--United States.; New York (State)--Politics and government.; United States--Foreign relations--Europe.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Censorship.; United States--Politics and government--1861-1865.; United States--Politics and government--1865-1900.
Titles
World (New York, N.Y.: 1860-1931)
Occupations
Editors.; Publishers.
Provenance
The papers of Manton Marble, editor and journalist, were given to the Library of Congress by Delia Marble and Lady Katrina Conway in 1931. An addition was transferred from the Library of Congress Archives in 1989.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Manton Marble are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1834, Nov. 16 Born, Worcester, Mass.
1855 Graduated, University of Rochester, Rochester, N.Y.
1862 1876 Editor and proprietor, New York World, New York, N.Y.
1864 Supported George B. McClellan for president Married Delia West (died 1869)
1874 Wrote platform for New York state Democratic Party
1876 Wrote platform for national Democratic Party
1878 Published Secret Chapter of Political History ... (New York: New York Sun )
1879 Married Abby Williams Lambard
1885 Delegate to European bimetallic congress
1917, July 24 Died, Allington Castle, Kent, England
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Manton Malone Marble (1834-1917) span the years 1838-1916 with the bulk of the material dating from 1864-1898. The collection consists of bound correspondence and related matter, including letters, telegrams, articles, and drafts of Democratic Party policy statements organized in three series: General Correspondence, Miscellany, and Addition.
Most of the collection relates to Marble’s career as editor and owner of the New York World and to his role in New York state and national Democratic Party politics in the period between the beginning of the Civil War and the close of the nineteenth century. There are drafts of statements and papers on the presidential election of 1876, a draft of the “Peace Plank” of the Democratic platform in 1864, articles on bimetallism and the Silver Question, papers relating to Marble’s role as President Grover Cleveland’s representative in Europe in 1885 to consult with European governments on bimetallism, and documents relating to the shutdown of the New York World in 1864 by the Abraham Lincoln administration.
The Miscellany series includes drafts of articles from the New York World, material relating to the election of 1876, bimetallism, the Manhattan Club, and the national Democratic party in the second half of the nineteenth century. The Addition contains one calling card.
Correspondents include Samuel Greene Arnold, Samuel L. M. Barlow, Thomas F. Bayard, August Belmont, W. H. Bogart, Calvert Comstock, Samuel Sullivan Cox, David G. Croly, George Ticknor Curtis, Charles A. Dana, James R. Doolittle, John Fiske, William Henry Hurlbert, Reverdy Johnson, Michael C. Kerr, Joseph Medill, Fitz-John Porter, John Finley Rathbone, Horatio Seymour, Richard Henry Stoddard, Samuel J. Tilden, Clement L. Vallandigham, Henry Watterson, and Horace White.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in three series:
General Correspondence, 1852-1916
Miscellany, 1838-1914
Addition
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1852-1916 (Box 1-93)
  Correspondence and related material in bound volumes.
  Arranged either chronologically or alphabetically.
  - 1852, Jan. 2-1858, Mar. 13 (Box 1)
  - 1858, Mar. 25-1862, Apr. 15 (Box 2)
  - 1862, Apr. 16-1863, Jan. 6 (Box 3)
  - 1863 (Box 4)
    - Jan. 7-July 14 (Box 4)
    - July 15-Nov. 11 (Box 5)
  - 1863, Nov. 12-1864, Apr. 8 (Box 6)
  - 1864 (Box 7)
    - Apr. 12-June 30 (Box 7)
    - July 1-Sept. 19 (Box 8)
    - Sept. 20-Oct. 29 (Box 9)
  - 1864, Oct. 31-1865, Mar. 4 (Box 10)
  - 1865, Mar. 7-Oct. 31 (Box 11)
  - 1865, Nov. 1- 1866, May 29 (Box 12)
  - 1866, June 4-Nov. 3 (Box 13)
  - 1866, Nov. 5-1867, May 15 (Box 14)
  - 1867, May 16-Oct. 24 (Box 15)
  - 1867, Oct. 25-1868, Jan. 25 (Box 16)
  - 1868 (Box 17)
    - Jan. 27-May 22 (Box 17)
    - May 25-Sept. 14 (Box 18)
    - Sept. 18-Nov. 2 (Box 19)
  - 1868, Nov. 3-1869, Feb. 10 (Box 20)
  - 1869 (Box 21)
    - Feb. 11-June 10 (Box 21)
    - June 15-Sept. 26 (Box 22)
    - Sept. 27-Dec. 30 (Box 23)
  - 1870 (Box 24)
    - Jan. 1-Apr. 25 (Box 24)
    - Apr. 26-Nov. 12 (Box 25)
    - Nov. 16-Dec. 31 (Box 26)
  - 1871 (Box 27)
    - Jan. 1-May 20 (Box 27)
    - May 21-Sept. 11 (Box 28)
    - Sept. 12-Nov. 25 (Box 29)
  - 1871, Dec. 2-1872, Mar. 13 (Box 30)
  - 1872, Mar. 14-Oct. 14 (Box 31)
  - 1872, Oct. 15-1873, Feb. 21 (Box 32)
  - 1873 (Box 33)
    - Feb. 26-June 24 (Box 33)
    - June 25-Nov. 14 (Box 34)
  - 1873, Nov. 15-1874, Feb. 20 (Box 35)
  - 1874 (Box 36)
    - Feb. 21-June 15 (Box 36)
    - June 17-Oct. 28 (Box 37)
    - Oct. 29-Dec. 31 (Box 38)
  - 1875 (Box 39)
    - Jan. 1-Mar. 11 (Box 39)
    - Mar. 12-June 20 (Box 40)
    - July 1-Oct. 9 (Box 41)
    - Oct. 11-Dec. 31 (Box 42)
  - 1876 (Box 43)
    - Jan. 1-Mar. 10 (Box 43)
    - Mar. 12-May 2 (Box 44)
    - May 3-June 28 (Box 45)
    - June 29-Sept. 30 (Box 46)
    - Oct. 2-Dec. 30 (Box 47)
  - 1877, Jan. 2-June 21 (Box 48)
  - 1877, June 25-1878, Feb. 20 (Box 49)
  - 1878, Feb. 21-Sept. 25 (Box 50)
  - 1878, Sept. 28-1879, June 27 (Box 51)
  - 1879, July 1-1880, May 16 (Box 52)
  - 1880, May 18-1881, May 24 (Box 53)
  - 1881, June 2-1882, Sept. 7 (Box 54)
  - 1882, Sept. 23-1884, Feb. 5 (Box 55)
  - 1884, Feb. 12-Aug. 21 (Box 56)
  - 1884, Aug. 22-1885, Feb. 21 (Box 57)
  - 1885 (Box 58)
    - Feb. 22-May 19 (Box 58)
    - May 28-Aug. 29 (Box 59)
    - Sept. 6-Nov. 18 (Box 60)
    - Nov. 19-Dec. 31 (Box 61)
  - 1886 (Box 62)
    - Jan. 1-Feb. 26 (Box 62)
    - Feb. 27-Apr. 23 (Box 63)
    - Apr. 24-Dec. 1 (Box 64)
  - 1886, Dec. 2-1887, Feb. 10 (Box 65)
  - 1887 (Box 66)
    - Feb. 11-Oct. 22 (Box 66)
  - 1887, Oct. 23-1888, Feb. 16 (Box 67)
  - 1888 (Box 68)
    - Feb. 17-July 17 (Box 68)
    - July 22-Dec. 30, undated (Box 69)
  - 1889, Jan. 1-1890, Apr. 5 (Box 70)
  - 1890, May 12-Sept. 15 (Box 71)
  - 1890, Sept. 19-1891, Jan. 4 (Box 72)
  - 1891 (Box 73)
    - Jan. 5-Apr. 26 (Box 73)
    - 4 Apr. 27-Nov. 4 (Box 74)
  - 1891, Nov. 6-1892, Jan. 10 (Box 75)
  - 1892 (Box 76)
    - Jan. 11-Apr. 2 (Box 76)
    - Apr. 4-July 24 (Box 77)
  - 1892, Aug. 5-1893, Mar. 1 (Box 78)
  - 1893, Mar. 2-Dec. 17 (Box 79)
  - 1893, Dec. 23-1895, Mar. 8 (Box 80)
  - 1895, Mar. 15-Sept. 5 (Box 81)
  - 1895, Sept. 7-1896, June 16 (Box 82)
  - 1896, June 25-1898, Feb. 16 (Box 83)
  - 1898, Feb. 19-1899, Dec. 17 (Box 84)
  - 1899, Dec. 27-1901, Oct. 18 (Box 85)
  - 1901, Oct. 21-1904, Feb. 9 (Box 86)
  - 1904, Feb. 16-1906, Dec. 7 (Box 87)
  - 1906, Dec. 24-1916, May 12 (Box 88)
  - Undated (Box 89)
    - “A-B” miscellaneous (Box 89)
    - “B-G” miscellaneous (Box 90)
    - Hurlbert, William Henry (Box 91)
    - “H-O” miscellaneous (Box 92)
    - “P-Y” miscellaneous (Box 93)
- Miscellany, 1838-1914 (Box 94-97)
  Correspondence, drafts of articles, financial records, newspaper clippings, photographs, proofs, and miscellaneous material.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject and chronologically therein.
  - Bound (Box 94)
    - Election of 1876 (Box 94)
      - Cipher telegrams (Box 94)
      - General (Box 95)
      - McLin, Samuel B., secretary of state of Florida (Box 95)
    - Silver memoranda, 1885-1886 (Box 95)
  - Unbound (Box 96)
    - Correspondence, 1838, 1866-1868, 1874-1875, 1888-1894, 1904, 1914, undated (Box 96)
    - Financial papers, 1864-1874, (5 folders) (Box 96)
    - Invitations and printed matter, 1878, 1885-1889, undated (Box 96)
    - Manhattan Club, New York, N.Y., 1864-1888, undated (Box 96)
    - “Silent Friend,” silver mine, 1892, undated (Box 96)
    - Writings (Box 96)
      - Drafts of articles and letters, 1872-1898, undated, (1 folder); (4 folders) (Box 96, Box 97)
      - Proofs, 1898, undated (Box 97)
- Addition (Box 97)
  Calling card.
  - Calling card, undated (Box 97)